Guide to the Stuart E. Knapp salmon poisoning research collection 1923-1999
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Stuart E. Knapp collection on Salmon Poisoning
1923-1999
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Knapp, S. E.
2470
Collection 2470, MtBC, us
0.4 linear feet
The Stuart E. Knapp salmon poisoning research collection consists of manuscripts, journal articles, and personal correspondence documenting Dr. Stuart E. Knapp's research on salmon poisoning. The bulk of Knapp's research files pertain directly to the evolution of study of the trematode Nanophyetus Salmoncola by Knapp, his contemporaries, and predecessors. They consist of handwritten notes taken while observing test subjects, results of testing, correspondence, and typewritten manuscript journal articles.
This collection is open for research.
Research papers created or collected by Stuart Knapp were donated to Montana State University Special Collections on January 27, 2005.
Research files in this collection have been maintained in the original order as provided by Dr. Knapp and most folder titles have been retained, with additional clarification added in parentheses. Whenever possible, citations to publications in which the research appeared have been listed with the manuscript articles.
Dr. Stuart E. Knapp was born on August 23, 1928 in Monroe, Washington. He attended Pacific University to obtain both his bachelor's and a master's before moving onto the University of Idaho, finishing his PhD in Parasitology at Kansas State University. Upon graduation, Dr. Knapp pursued a career as a professor and administrator at various institutions of higher learning before accepting the position of Vice President of Academic Affairs at Montana State in 1978. He continued to actively participate in his field, including conducting research on a variety of topics within the parasitology and veterinary medicine fields.
Salmon poisoning is caused by the microorganism Rickettsia that lives within members of the Salmonid family. Most cases of Salmon poisoning occur when canids eat dead fish or their remains from riverbanks that are prevalent during spawning. Salmon poisoning is mostly found along the western slope of the Cascade mountains. After canids ingest the poisoned fish, they become ill within seven to twelve days. Before extensive research into the cause, an infected canid had a ninety percent chance of the disease becoming fatal. In the early 1920s, Dr. Bennett T. Simms, a professor of veterinary medicine at the Oregon Agricultural College (now Oregon State University) in Corvallis, began collecting research data on salmon poisoning. His work was continued by Dr. J. N. Shaw, also of OSU, in the 1940s. Dr. Knapp collected the research notes of Simms and Shaw during the course of his own work on the topic.
The Stuart E. Knapp salmon poisoning research collection consists of manuscripts, journal articles, and personal correspondence documenting Dr. Stuart E. Knapps research on salmon poisoning. The bulk of Knapp's research files pertain directly to the evolution of study of the trematode Nanophyetus Salmoncola by Knapp, his contemporaries, and predecessors. They consist of handwritten notes taken while observing test subjects, results of testing, correspondence, and typewritten manuscript journal articles.
Authors of collected manuscript articles include: D. F. Sinitsin, Bennett T. Simms, D. R. Donham, J. N. Shaw, A. M. McCapes, Raymond E. Millemann, O. H. Muth, Elwin E. Bennington, Karl B. Hanson, Emile F. Pernot, Nathan Fasten, and Fred W. Miller.
All substantial publication offprints have been removed for item level cataloging.
Canidae--Diseases; Nanophyetus salminicola; Rickettsial diseases in animals; Parasitologists-Montana-Bozeman
Disease; Fisheries and Wildlife; Montana; Bozeman
- Early notes of Simms, Shaw, Donham, and Sinitsin (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Simms, "Salmon Poisoning" (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Research notes (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence-Salmon Poisoning (mostly B.T. Simms and C.R. Donham), 1924-1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Salmoning of Dogs, Pernot (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Common Animal Parasites of Fishes, Fasten, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anhelminic Efficiency of Carbon Tetrachlorid in the Treatment of Foxes, Hanson and VanVolkenberg; Journal of Agricultural Research, 1924 April 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - So Called Salmon Poisoning of Dogs, Donham. Science, 1925 February (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Are Salmon Poison and Distemper the Same Disease?, Outdoor Life, 1925 May (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence and research notes (mostly J.W. Shaw) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence and manuscripts-Salmon Poisoning (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - So Called Salmon Poisoning of Dogs, Donham, Simms, Miller (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Salmon Poisoning, Simms, Donham, Shaw (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Salmon Poisoning: Transmission and Immunization Experiment, Simms, McCapes, Muth (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Coyote Susceptible to Salmon Poisoning, Donham and Simms (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Use of Terramycin and Magnamycin in the Treatment of Experimental Salmon Poisoning in Dogs, Ott and Gorham (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Salmon Poisoning proposal (research grant application of Raymond E. Millemann) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Blood counts (from dogs exposed by feeding or injection) (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Blood sedimentations (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Blood studies-Fibrinogen Content and microscopic examinations (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Cercariae number in snail and Cercariae destruction with electricity (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Eggs hatching (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Examinations other species than SALMONIDAE (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Hyperimmune blood lots (experiments), 1931-1933 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Hyperimmune serum sent veterinarians, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Immunization-Inheritance, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Immunization studies, 1931-1933 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Medicinal treatments, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Metacercariae storage/longevity, 1929-1931 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Mixed serum lots; series M, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Snails-Distribution, longevity, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Tissue vaccines (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Treated blood (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Knapp-Milleman research, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Hosts and Distribution of Capillaria Bovis (Schnyder) in Domestic and Wild, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Ruminants in Northwestern United States, Worley, Barrett, Knapp (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Rickettsial Diseases, Farrell (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Knapp and Millemann notes, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Manuscript/article materials (Russian publications) (Box 1, Folder 26)